Guide to the Joseph Spence Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Joseph Spence papers
1649-1859
1739-1768
OSB MSS 4
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
7.75
(10 boxes)
The papers include correspondence, personal papers, notes and memoranda, and related papers. Much of the material concerns Spence's Anecdotes, including manuscripts of his notes on conversations with Alexander Pope, memoranda on Stephen Duck and other authors, and notes on Spence's reading. There are also extensive notes on English gardens, shorter writings by Spence, and drafts of works which appeared in his Moralities (1753, under the pseudonym of Sir Harry Beaumont). The correspondence principally concerns personal and business matters, including the settlement of Spence's estate. Series VIII, Derby Anecdotes (Oversize) contains a large paper extra-illustrated set of the Anecdotes (1820) with autograph documents bound in,including autographs of Eustace Budgell, Colley Cibber, William Congreve, George II, Charles Montagu, Earl of Halifax, David Mallet, Alexander Pope, Sir William Trumbull, and Joseph Warton.
Spence, Joseph, 1699-1768
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were the gift of James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Joseph Spence Papers consist of correspondence, writings, and notes and memoranda of Joseph Spence, as well as a three volume extra-illustrated copy of Spence's Anecdotes (1820).
The Spence Papers are divided into eight series. Many of them, particularly those in Series IV, V, and VII, are related to the Anecdotes. A complete discussion of the complex editorial history of Spence's work can be found in the introduction to Joseph Spence, Observations, Anecdotes and Characters of Books and Men, edited by James M. Osborn (Oxford, 1966).
Series I, Correspondence (Boxes 1-2), is arranged alphabetically by correspondent and contains letters to and by Joseph Spence and several other individuals. A number of original letters are bound in the three volumes of the Derby Anecdotes, and cross-references for these to the volumes can be found in the list for Series I.
Series II, Documents--Legal, Financial and Ecclesiastical, is housed in Box 2, folders 54-66 and consists of documents relating to Spence's life and career, including his certificate of ordination, his appointment to the Professorship of Modern History at Oxford, and the articles of agreements between Spence and publisher James Dodsley for the rights to Spence's work.
Series III, Spence Travel Letters for 1739-1741, is located in Box III and consists of photostats of letters from Spence to his mother, the originals of which are part of B. M. Egerton 2234.
Boxes 4 and 5 hold Series IV, Notes and Memoranda, which has been organized alphabetically by subject or occasionally by author. It includes notes on history and on Spence's reading; unpublished memoranda of conversations with Stephen Duck; and copies of works by other authors. Box 5, folders 135-52 contains writings by Spence himself, including "The Dream of Atticus," "Religious Fooleries," and drafts of various works published in Moralities (1753).
Series V, Gardening Notes, contains notes on and plans for various gardens throughout England, including Byfleet, Knole, Oatlands, and Prestonfield. Series VI, Miscellaneous and Indexes, located in Box 7, folders 215-23, contains photocopies of other sources of the Anecdotes and other material relating to the Spence Papers, including a copy of the sale catalogue and an index of names.
Loose Papers for the Anecdotes, Series VII, is housed is Box 7, folders 224-77. Numbered 1-54, these papers are the earliest notes of conversations by Spence; they have been described in detail in James M. Osborn's edition of Observations, Anecdotes, and Characters, xlvi-lxxiii. Each numbered anecdote is housed in a separate folder.
Series VIII, Derby Anecdotes (Oversize), is located in Boxes 8-10 and consists of the three volumes of the Derby Anecdotes and a photocopy of A Catalogue of the Entire Libraries of the Rev. Mr. Joseph Spence.
Authors, English; English literature -- Anecdotes; English literature -- 18th century; Gardens -- England -- Design; Gardens, English -- Design; Literature -- Anecdotes; Europe -- Description and travel -- Early works to 1800; Europe -- Description and travel; Great Britain -- Intellectual life -- 18th century; Autographs (manuscripts); Anecdotes, observations, and characters, of books and men; Budgell, Eustace, 1686-1737 -- Autograph; Cibber, Colley, 1671-1757 -- Autograph; Cocchi, Antonio, 1695-1758; Congreve, William, 1670-1729 -- Autograph; Dodsley, James, 1724-1797; Duck, Stephen, 1705-1756; Lawman, Mary; Lee, Harry, 1721-1789; Lowth, Robert, 1710-1787; Mallet, David, 1705?-1765 -- Autograph; Halifax, Charles Montagu, Earl of, 1661-1715 -- Autograph; Pope, Alexander, 1688-1744; Richardson, Samuel, 1689-1761; Ridley, Glocester, 1702-1774; Rolle, Edward, 1703-1791; Spence, Joseph, 1699-1768; Trumbull, William, Sir, 1639-1716 -- Autograph; Warton, Joseph, 1722-1800 -- Autograph
- Correspondence, 1735 Jun 21; Series I
  - Allen, Ralph, 1694-1764 ALS to his sister, Widcomby, 1735 Jun 21
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: Series VIII, Derby Anecdotes, Box 8, folder 278
  - Alston, Philip ALS to Joseph Spence, Poplar, 1748 Jan 8 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    1 p., with address; 20 x 30 cm.
    On back, Spence's jottings for his
    letter to Samuel Richardson
    (1689-1761) of 21 Jan 1748.
  - Bedford, duke of, servant to Letter (copy) to servant of Earl of Sunderland, no place (Box 1, Folder 2)
    1 p.; 16 x 10 cm.
    A petition to Sunderland for a
    fellow ship for a former tutor; copy
    in Spence's hand.
  - Buckingham, John Villiers, 1677?-1723 Document signed, to Russell Robartes of Her Majesty's Exchequer, no place, 1712 Apr 16
  - Budgell, Eustace, 1686-1737 Letter to an author of the Prompter, [London], 1735 Oct 23
  - Cawsey, Mrs. 3 ALS to Gloster Ridley (1702-1774), Guildford, 1770 Jul-Dec (Box 1, Folder 3)
    4 p., with address; 23 x 18 cm.
    Concerning a demand for payment of a
    bill for a person Spence had placed
    as an apprentice; one letter has a
    draft of Ridley's reply.
  - Cheap, David Letter (copy) to Richard Lindsay, Chile 1744 Feb 26 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    4 p.; 32 x 20 cm.
    Cheap relates the story of the mutiny
    on HMS Wager in 1741, under his
    command; copy in Spence's hand.
  - Cibber, Colley, 1671-1757 Receipt signed, Drury Lane Theatre, 1716 May 28
  - Cocchi, Antonio, 1665-1758 Letter (translation of) to Joseph Spence, in Spence' hand, no place (Box 1, Folder 5)
    4 p.; 19 x 15 cm.
    Cocchi gives his thoughts on esta-
    blishing a general ethical principle.
  - Coltman, Elizabeth (Cartwright) ALS to Gloster Ridley (1702-1774), Leicester, 1769 Feb 20 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    1 p., with address; 24 x 19 cm.
    Concerns dispersal of Spence's
    possessions.
  - Congreve, William, 1670-1729 Document signed, to John Warner, no place, 1716 Nov 23
  - Cowper, William Cowper, 1st earl, d. 1723 ALS to a Mrs. Robinson, [London?], 1710 Jan 15
  - Dick, Sir Alexander, 1703-1785 LS (photostat) to Joseph Spence, Prestonfield, 1767 Dec 25 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    4 p.; 20 x 16 cm.
    Tells of the recent marriages of his
    two nieces, the Misses Douglas
    mentions own activities; concerns
    Thomas Blacklock (1721-1791); from
    the Newcastle Papers at Nottingham.
  - Dodsley, James, 1724-1797 2 ALS to Gloster Ridley (1702-1774), 1768 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    2 p., with addresses; 23 x 19 cm.
    Concerns Spence's gift to Mrs. Lawman
    and payment of debt from Mr. Harrup.
  - Duck, Stephen, 1705-1756 ALS to Joseph Spence, no place, [ca. 1746] (Box 1, Folder 9)
    1 p.; 26 x 20 cm.
    Duck tells of lodgings at Kew which
    Spence might rent; on back, Spence
    has written a fable of Minos, which
    was published in 1746 in Museum.
  - Elliott, John 3 ALS to Gloster Ridley (1702-1774), Byfleet, 1768 Sep-Nov (Box 1, Folder 10)
    3 p., with addresses; various sizes
  - George II, King of Gt.Brit., 1683-1760 Document signed, to Commissioners of the Treasury, Court of St. James, 1716 Dec 31
  - George II, King of Gt. Brit., 1683-1760 Document signed, Kensington, 1739 Jul 23
  - Halifax, Charles Montagu, 1st earl of, 1661-1715 Document signed, [London], 1711 Mar 26
    See: Derby Anecdotes, Box 8, folder 278
  - Hampden, Robert Hampden-Trevor, 1st viscount, 1706-1783 ALS to an unnamed recipient [Spence?], Hague, 1742 Mar 13 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    2 p.; 23 x 19 cm.
    Expressing his sorrow for the death
    of Sir Richard Ellys (1688?-1742).
  - Harrup, Henry 2 LS to Gloster Ridley (1702-1774), 1768 Nov 13 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Great Horwood, 1769 May 18
    2 p., with addresses; 21 x 16 cm.
    Concerns Harrup's debt to Spence
    estate for rent of Great Horwood.
  - Herbert, Miss AL (?) to Joseph Spence, no place, n. d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    1 p.; 16 x 16 cm.
    A gift of, and request for, verse.
  - Hill, Jonathan ALS to Joseph Spence, Brandon, 1758 Sep 21 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    2p., with address; 18 x 30 cm.
    Requests Spence's opinion on his
    poetry.
  - Irvine, Jenny (Douglas) ALS (photostat) to German, Relhead, 1764 Apr 15 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    18 p.; 25 x 15 cm.
    Recounts her engagement to Austruther
    with Spence's note; also with copy of
    extracts from letters produced by
    Austruther; from the Newcastle Papers
    at Nottingham.
  - James II, king of Gt.Brit., 1633-1701 Document signed, Windsor, 1671 May 30
  - Jameson, Richard ALS to Joseph Spence, Danzig, 1768 Aug 27 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    3 p., with address; 23 x 19 cm.
    Asks Spence to write, refers to
    Thomas Blacklock (1721-1791) and
    Edward Holdsworth (1684-1746).
    With: encomium in Latin on
    Archbishop Wickham
  - Lawman, Mary 6 ALS to Gloster Ridley (1702-1774), 1768-69 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Cambridge
    7 p., with addresses; various sizes
    Concerns annuity to Mrs. Lawman from
    Spence estate; includes on one, a
    draft of Ridley's reply, 1769 Apr 11.
  - Lee, Harry, 1721-1789 ALS to Gloster Ridley (1702-1774), Coton, 1769 May 22 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    2 p., with address; 23 x 19 cm.
    Concerning Winchester College and
    Spence's legacy to the to the
    "Wiccamical Society".
  - Lesslie, John ALS to Joseph Spence, Libbertton Kirk, 1760 Sep 20 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    1 p.; 19 x 15 cm.
    Relates the differences between
    Scottish and English statute acres.
  - Louis XIV, king of France, 1637-1715 Document signed, to [governor of Laguenau?], Compregne, 1649 May 20
  - Lowth, Robert, bp. of London, 1710-1787 23 ALS to Gloster Ridley (1702-1774), various places, 1768-69 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    ca. 57 p. with addresses; 23 x 19 cm.
    Concerns actions of Lowth and Ridley
    as executors of Spence's estate.
  - Lowth, Robert, bp. of London, 1710-1787 ALS (photostat) to Joseph Spence, Durham, 1762 Mar 2 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    6 p.; 20 x 16 cm.
    Discusses the poetry of Ossian
    relates to Edward Noel Wentworth,
    1st Viscount, (1715-1774); from
    Newcastle Papers at
    Nottingham.
  - Mallet, David, ?1705-1765 Receipt signed, no place, n. d.
  - Marchmont, Alexander Hume Campbell, 2nd earl of, 1675-1740 Document signed, Cambray, 1724 Dec 12
  - Massingberd, Ann 3 letters (copies) to Philippa Massingberd, Ormesby, 1757 Feb-Mar (Box 1, Folder 22)
    11 p.; various sizes
    Mentions Spence's improvements at
    Ormesby and a legend; concerns Joseph
    Addison (1672-1719); copies in
    Spence's hand.
  - Onslow, Arthur, 1691-1768 Receipt signed, no place, 1738 May 7
  - Oxford, Robert Harley, 1st earl of, 1661-1724 Document signed, to Charles Lord Halifax, Whitehall, 1712 Jul 10
  - Peterborough, Charles Mordaunt, 3rd earl of, 1658-1735 Document signed, to Commissary for hand Service, Lisbon, 1705 Jun 13
  - Pope, Alexander, 1688-1744 ALS to unnamed recipient, Twickenham, 1730 Aug 14
  - Richardson, Samuel, 1689-1761 ALS to Joseph Spence, London, 1749 Oct 30 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    1 p.; 18 x 15 cm.
    Inquires about not having heard
    recently from Spence.
  - Ridley, Gloster, 1702-1774 ALS (draft) to Henry Harrup, [?Poplar], [1769] Jun 2 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    1 p.; 20 x 16 cm.
    Concerning Harrup's debt to Spence
    estate for Great Horwood; notes on
    back about the matter.
  - Ridley, Gloster, 1702-1774 ALS (draft-photocopy) to Harry Lee (1721-1789), [?Poplar], [ca. 1769 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    1 p.; 16 x 15 cm.
    Concerns Spence's legacy to Super-
    annuates' Fund of Winchester College.
  - Robson, James, 1733-18O6 ALS to Gloster Ridley (1702-1774), London, 1768 Aug 29 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    1 p., with address; 22 x 18 cm.
    Concerns the possible sale of the
    library of the late Joseph Spence.
  - Roland, Monsieur ALS to [?Joseph Spence], Reims, 1737 Aug 13 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    2 p., with address; 22 x 17 cm.
    M. Roland sends a sample of fine
    wine, addressed to "M. Trevor
    [John Morley Trevor (d. 1745)], à
    la galère, à Blois".
  - Rolle, Edward, 1703-1791 14 ALS to Gloster Ridley (1702-1774), Berwick and other places, 1768-69 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    ca. 38 p., with addresses; various
    sizes
    Concerns business as executors of
    Spence's estate.
  - Rolle, Henry, 1709-1750 ALS to Joseph Spence, no place, 1729 Jul 12 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    2 p., with address; 20 x 22 cm.
    Asks for news of "learned world"; on
    back, Spence's notes from Memoirs of
    Duke of Buckingham [Buckingham,
    George Villiers, 2d Duke of,
    (1628-1687).
  - Sharp, Thomas, 1693-1758 ALS to Joseph Spence, Rothbury, 1756 Jun 15 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Mentions an exchange with Robert
    Lowth, Bp. of London (1710-1787)
    stewardship at Durham.
  - Smith, John ALS to Gloster Ridley (1702-1774), Cambridge, 1769 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    1 p., with address; 21 x 17 cm.
    On behalf of Mrs. Lawman, concerning
    request to sell her annuity.
  - Spence, Joseph, 1699-1768 8 ALS (photostats) to Antonio Cocchi (1665-1768), various places, 1732-52 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    16 p.; various sizes
    Mentions his translations and Lord
    Lincoln [Henry Fiennes Clinton, 2nd
    duke of Newcastle (1720-1794)]; asks
    Cocchi's help with contacts in
    literati; mentions Polymetis, Crito, introduces friends to
    Cocchi; mentions Robert Lowth, bp. of
    London (1710- 1787), Henry Fiennes
    Clinton, 2nd duke of Newcastle
    (1720-1794), and Edward Rolle
    (1703-1791).
  - Spence, Joseph, 1699-1768 ALS to Elizabeth (Cartwright) Coltman, Byfleet, 1767 Jan 5 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    2 p.; 19 x 19 cm.
    A friendly note.
  - Spence, Joseph, 1699-1768 ALS (photostat) to Henry Hoare (1705- 1785), Byfleet, 1766 Mar 24 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    7 p.; 23 x 15 cm.
    An account of the Grotto of Lord
    duke of Newcastle (1720-1794) at
    Oatlands; from the Newcastle Papers
  - Spence, Joseph, 1699-1768 LS (photostat) to Mrs. Johnson, Byfleet, 1763 Oct 21 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    4 p.; 21 x 16 cm.
    Spence relates story of predictions
    of deaths by John Need in 1707
    quoting an account by Dr. Fletcher of
    Winchester College; see JMO Anecdotes
    984.
  - Spence, Joseph, 1699-1768 AL (copy) to Bennet Langton (1737-1801), no place, [after (Box 1, Folder 36)
    1 p.; 32 x 20 cm.
    Spence's reflections on death, on the
    occassion of the death of Langton's
    brother George Ferne Langton.
  - Spence, Joseph, 1699-1768 Letter (copy) to William Massingberd (1719-1802), Byfleet, 1765 May 17 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Spence gives news of common
    acquaintances.
  - Spence, Joseph, 1699-1768 43 ALS (photostats) to Newcastle, Henry Fiennes Clinton, 2nd duke of, 1720-1794, various places, 1745-68 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    ca. 175 p., with address
    various sizes.
    Abundant material from a continuing
    friendship; photostats from the
    Newcastle Papers at Nottingham; with
    2 AL, 2 AL (drafts), and autograph
    notes for one letter, all in the same
    series; relates to Henry St. John,
    1st viscount Bolingbroke (1678-1751),
    Henry Vane, 2nd earl of Darlington
    (ca. 1705-1758), Samuel Dashwood,
    Sir Alexander Dick (1703-1764),
    Robert Dodsley (1703-1764), Henry
    Hoare (1705-1785), William Hoare
    (1707?-1792), Edward Holdworth
    (1684-1746), Robert Lowth, bp. of
    London (1710-1787), Charles Spencer,
    3rd duke of Marlborough (1706-1758),
    William Massingberd (1719-1802).
    Also relates to Horace Walpole,
    4th earl of Orford (1717-1797),
    John Robartes, 4th earl of Radnor
    (1686-1757), Charles Lennox,
    2nd duke of Richmond, Lennox,
    and Aubigny (1701-1750), Edward Rolle
    (1703-1791), William Shenstone
    (1714-1763), Philip Southcote
    (1699?-1758), Richard Trevor, bp. of
    Durham (1707-1771), William
    Warburton, bp. of Gloucester (1698-
    1779), Edward Noel Wentworth, 1st
    viscount Wentworth (1715-1774)
    mentions Charliad; in three
    folders.
  - Spence, Joseph, 1699-1768 ALS to Christopher Pitt (1699-1768), London, 1739 May 4 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    2 p., with address; 20 x 28 cm.
    Spence advises Pitt on committing
    himself to some writing project.
  - Spence, Joseph, 1699-1768 AL (draft) to Samuel Richardson (1689- 1761), [London], 1748 Jan 21 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    5 p.; 33 x 20 cm.
    Spence comments on Clarissa.
  - Spence, Joseph, 1699-1768 2 ALS to Samuel Richardson (1689-1761), Byfleet, Berwick St. John, 1758, 1759 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    6 p.; 19 x 23 cm.
    Concerning the conduct of his cousin
    Harry Lawman; with copies of both and
    of a third letter to Richardson in
    the same series.
  - Spence, Joseph, 1699-176B 3 ALS to Mirabella (Collier) Spence, (1670?-1756), various places [1722?]-36 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    13 p.; various sizes
    A youthful poem on William III and
    Anne; story of the African, Job St.
    Solomon.
  - Spence, Joseph, 1699-1768 ALS (draft) to [?James] Thomson (1700- 1748), no place, [1730 May 12?] (Box 2, Folder 43)
    Spence tells of meeting John Dennis
    (1657-1734), the aged critic; with
    Spence's notes on the allowance to a
    maid of honor, "Lady Lucye", in Henry
    VIII's time.
  - Spence, Joseph, 1699-1768 ALS (copy) to [?John Morley] Trevor (d. 1745), no place, 1738 Oct 5 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    1 p.; 21 x 17 cm.
    Letter in an exaggerated style,
    "Essex-Stile" [?].
  - Spence, Joseph, 1699-1768 AL (draft) to Robert Wheeler, (d. 1763) no place, 1751 Sep 19 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    Spence gives his rules for designing
    gardens, and describes his
    improvements at Byfleet; with three
    additional copies of the letter.
  - Spence, Joseph, 1699-1768 Receipt signed, to John Weir, no place, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 46)
    1 p.; 5 x 16 cm.
    Receipt of payment for a copy of the
    poems of Thomas Blacklock (1721-1791)
  - Spence, Mirabella (Collier), ?1670-?1756 ALS to Joseph Spence (1699-1768), no place, 1734 May 7 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    A chatty letter, Spence's jottings on
    back.
  - Spence, Richard, 1701- ALS to Mirabella (Collier) Spence (1670?-1756), London, 1737 May 28 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    2 p., with address; 31 x 19 cm.
    Gives news of the African, Job St.
  - Thoms, William, 1803-1885 AL to Peter Cunningham (1816-1869), no place, 1859 Apr 25 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    1 p.; 18 x 11 cm.
    Thoms inquires after Ms. B, missing
    at Singer sale [Samuel Weller Singer
    (1783-1858)]; on back, ALS Cunningham
    to Thoms of 23 Apr.
  - Trumbull, Sir William, 1639-1716 Document signed, Whitehall, 1696 Aug 17
  - Warburton, William, bp of Gloucester, 1698-1779 ALS to unnamed recipient, no place, 1776 May 8
  - Warton, Joseph, 1722-18OO ALS to G. Jones, [?Winchester], 1792 Nov 11
  - Wastell, Edward 3 ALS to Gloster Ridley (1702-1774), Guildford, 1768 Oct-Dec 29 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    3 p., with addresses; 21 x 32 cm.
    Concerning money from sale of the
    possessions of Joseph Spence (1699-
    1768).
  - White, Benjamin, 1725-1794 3 ALS to Gloster Ridley (1702-1774), Fleet Street, 1768-69 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    3 p., with addresses; 33 x 21 cm.
    Concerning the sale of the library of
    Joseph Spence (1699-1768); on back of
    last, Ridley's affidavit on Spence's
    death.
  - Whitmore, Edward, 1733-1816 3 ALS to Gloster Ridley (1702-1774), Oxford, 1768-69 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    8 p.; various sizes
    Inquiring the value of the living at
    Great Horwood, and the rent of Mr.
    Harrup.
  - [Unnamed correspondent] Letter (draft) to Simon Harcourt, 1st earl Harcourt (1714-1777), Hensol, 1738 Aug 2 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    9 p.; 23 x 19 cm.
    A romantic account of the scene of a
    cave at St. Donat's with quotations
    from Virgil.
- Documents--Legal, Financlal and Ecclesiastical, Series II
  - Will of Joseph Spence Senior, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Ordination into priesthood, 1726 Jun 5 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Arcadia, College of, diploma of membership for Joseph Spence, 1741 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Oxford, Orders relating to the Professorship of Modern History, 1742 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Newcastle, Henry Pelham Clinton, 2d Duke of, 1720-1794
    - DS: pension of L105 given to Spence, 1742 Apr 28 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Rectory of Great Horwood, granted to Spence, 1742 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Prebendary at Durham, Spence's installation in, 1754 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Professorship of Modern History at Oxford, Spence appointment to, 1761 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Certification of having taken the Sacrament, at Byfleet, 1762 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Prebendary at Durham, Spence's dispensation from, 1766 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Articles of agreement between Spence and James Dodsley for rights to Spence's published and unpublished work, 1767 Mar 24 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Will of Joseph Spence, 1699-1768, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Executor's Accounts, dispersal of Spence estate, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 66)
- Spence Travel Letters for 1739-1741., Series III
  These are photocopies of the original letters,
  part of B.M. Egerton MS. 2234, leaves 131-291.
  - ALSs by Spence to his mother (photostats) Various places in Italy and France, 1739-41 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - ALS (photostat) by Ld Lincoln to Mrs Spence, Paris, 1741 Sep 9 (Box 3, Folder 68)
- Notes & Memoranda, Series IV
  - Africa, descriptions of travel in northern, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Art: Notes on painters, beauty, and particular paintings (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Blandy, Mary, d. 1752
    - Note about her trial., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - Boerhaave, Hermann, 1668-1738
    - Account of his life and writings, from a work by Dr. William Burton. (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - Books: catalogue of a library, 1749 (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Brand, Sir Thomas, ca. 1669-1761
    - Poetry, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - Buxton, Jedidiah, 1707-1772
    - Notes on, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - Chesterfield, Philip Dormer Stanhope, 4th earl of, 1694-1773:
    - Poetry by, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Cicero, reading from, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Courayer, Pierre Francois, le, 1681-1776
    - Address in Spencc's hand, conferring a doctorate degree on Courrayer. Oxford, 1727 Aug 23 (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - With an address by Courrayer in gratitude for same award.
  - de Costena, Michael, fl. ca. 1738
    - History of the captain of a captured trading vessel., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Dodsley, James and Robert
    - List of authors of their Select Fables, 1761 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Dryden, John, 1631-1700
    - Notes on, [1760 or later] (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Duck, Stephen, 1705-1756
    - Notes on conversations with, in 1730 Not published in Anecdotes., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - England: History of, notes and materials on (Box 4, Folder 83)